Might the diabetes drug Metformin
have an anti-aging effect?
Check out this 3-video series to see
what the science says.
"Does Metformin Work
as a Life-Extension Drug?"
The noxious weed goat's rue
was widely used
as an herbal medicine
back in the Middle Ages for
thirst and frequent urination,
what we now know of
as a cardinal symptom
and sign of diabetes.
The plant produces
a mitochondrial poison
known as galegine.
One can imagine
how this could help discourage
grazing herbivores,
but why would crippling
mitochondrial function
help with diabetes?
Well, if you got the dose
just right,
you could impair
energy production just enough
to spring AMPK into action.
AMPK would then dial down
the liver's
energy-intensive process
of sugar production,
and blood sugars would fall.
Galegine proved too toxic
for use in humans
(and presumably goats)
but was tweaked
into a milder form in the 1950s.
That's the origin story
of metformin,
now, even 60+ years later
the most widely prescribed
diabetes drug in the world.
Sold originally as Glucophage
(meaning "sugar eater"),
metformin is
now prescribed annually
more than 90 million times
in the U.S. alone.
Despite all the strides
in biotechnology,
Big Pharma has yet
to come up with a safer,
more effective
first-line treatment
for type 2 diabetes
than a drug
that retails
at pennies per pill.
Ramping up AMPK
isn't all that metformin does
(for example, it also appears
to foster the growth
of good bacteria
in the gut).
But the AMPK boost alone
would be expected
to have
wide-ranging health effects.
Remember, AMPK is activated
when resources are scarce;
so, it causes the body
to hunker down
into energy-conservation mode
and put the brakes
on new construction projects.
So, no more making excess
blood sugar or cholesterol.
Time to start tapping
into the larder.
And, indeed, metformin doesn't
just lower sugars in the blood
but cholesterol and body fat.
And shutting down
the excess synthesis of proteins
can also have health benefits.
Fibrosis is the accumulation
of scar tissue
in response
to an inflammatory insult.
As a transient,
localized phenomenon,
fibrosis helps heal wounds
and repair damaged tissue,
but in response to the systemic
inflammation of aging,
surplus scar tissue
can build up in our heart,
liver, kidneys, and lungs.
Excess fibrosis is estimated
to contribute to 45 percent
of all death
in the United States.
But AMPK switches the body
into miser mode,
shrinking the energy budget
for such superfluous activities
and ratchets down
fibrotic processes.
The AMPK priorities shift
from growth to preservation
might also be expected
to slow cancer progression.
Based on dozens
of observational studies
involving tens of thousands
of diabetic cancer patients,
those on metformin
did indeed experience
a significant
survival advantage,
correlating with
a 26 percent decreased risk
of dying from cancer.
No wonder there are
more than 100 ongoing studies
to put metformin
to the test against cancer.
As the director of Harvard's
Cancer Center put it,
"Metformin may have
already saved more people
from cancer deaths
than any drug in history."
If AMPK plays such a key role
in the aging process,
and metformin boosts AMPK,
can metformin slow aging
and lengthen lifespans?
It certainly can
in some species.
C. elegans worms fed metformin
maintained a youthful state
and can exhibit
a nearly 40 percent increase
in average survival.
Interfere with
the AMPK pathway, though,
and this
lifespan extension disappears,
confirming the role of AMPK
in metformin's
anti-aging effects.
Metformin also improves
the healthspans
and lifespans of mice,
but failed to extend
the lives of rats,
calling the pro-longevity
effects of metformin
into question.
The dose they used
(15 times that used in humans)
may have been too high, however,
and the F344 rats they used
are an inbred strain
(named after the 344th
brother sister mating)
that are resistant
to the health benefits
of calorie restriction.
Since metformin
acts through AMPK
as a calorie
restriction mimetic,
it stands to reason
that these animals
may be less prone
to metformin's effects.
What about humans?
Unlike other potential
anti-aging drugs
in the pipeline,
we have the benefit of data
on more than
a million study subjects
who have been tracked
in metformin trials.
And, indeed,
compared to diabetics
who take drugs
other than metformin,
those on metformin
appear protected
from age-related
susceptibilities,
like fractures,
or serious infections,
glaucoma,
and cognitive impairment.
Most importantly,
diabetics who take metformin
live significantly longer
than those taking different
blood sugar-lowering drugs.
Doesn't that prove metformin
is a pro-longevity drug?
No.
For example, maybe metformin
just controlled
their diabetes better.
Researchers still found
a survival benefit
for diabetics on metformin
compared to those
as well managed on other drugs,
but maybe the other drugs
were shortening lifespans,
and so, metformin
just looked good in comparison.
How could you try
to tease out the effects?
What if you
compared the lifespans
of diabetics on metformin
to nondiabetics?
Now, that's not really
a fair comparison.
Any benefits metformin has
could easily
be outweighed and masked
by the life-limiting
nature of diabetes--
unless, that is,
the diabetics on metformin
actually lived longer.
Longer than nondiabetics.
And,
are you sitting down?
That's exactly
what the research shows.
Diabetics placed on metformin
went on to live longer lives
than those who never
got diabetes in the first place.
From a longevity standpoint,
it's as if they got lucky
to be diagnosed with diabetes,
because then, they had access
to this lifespan-enhancing drug.
So, wait.
If metformin is so powerful
as to more than offset
such a dreaded diagnosis,
should everyone
be taking metformin?
What are the downsides?
That's exactly what
I'm gonna be covering next.